hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan so yesterday I made a video
on Spring Boot interceptors and I see
lot of comments regarding filters versus
interceptors and what is Filters
specifically uh so I I what I
anticipated from this is that there are
lot of doubts between when to use filter
when to use Interceptor what is the
exact difference so today I will discuss
uh about this and I hope that after this
video your doubts will get clarified and
like you can easily decide when to go
for filter when to go for Interceptor
okay let's start without wasting any
time so let's before even seeing further
right let's see this oneliner definition
right and even though if you don't
understand any of this terms it's okay
because once we go further after that we
will come back again and then we read
this it will make more sense so filter
it intercept the sttp request and
response before they reach to the
subet okay and what is Interceptor says
it's specific to Spring framework and
intercept HTTP request and response
before they reach to the controller or I
would say that before they reach to the
controller and after
subet okay so read it one more time it
filter intercept the HTTP request and
response before the request reach to the
sulet and Interceptor is after
sulet but before controller okay so just
keep this in mind and we'll proceed
further this two definition will get
clear soon so if you remember this
diagram which I have discussed in the
first video of a spring boot discussion
and in yesterday also in the uh
intercept video so we know that right
when a request comes
in our sulet
container catches it and it will pass it
to one of the sulet so in Spring boot we
have a dispatcher sulet dispatcher sub
takes care of couple of things right
which controller this request should go
right and it will create an instance and
it will ultimately invoke that
controller okay so this is I hope it's
clear but now let's see this one I have
further drilled down this diagram to
understand the filter and Interceptor
more when the request comes in so here
if you say when the request comes in it
goes to our sulet container in that case
let's say
tomcat now when the
Tomcat or sulet container get this HTTP
request what it will do is before
assigning to a sulet particular
subet our filter comes into the picture
we can have multiple filter filter one
Filter 2 it's a generally they call as a
chain of filters right so after filter
one filter two will run if there are
more filters that will run and after
that one of the specific sulet will get
involved right now let's say that if we
are running a spring boot then
dispatcher subet will get involed and
and this dispatcher subet now here is
our
Interceptor
so before this dispatcher subet handles
the request to controller our
interceptors comes into the picture here
so with this diagram now you should uh
see that where the filter lies in and
where the interceptors lies in so filter
lies in before the request handed over
to
suent and interceptors lies before the
request handed over to
controllers okay so now with this one
few doubts might have come to your mind
that hey first of all what is sulet is
it possible that more than one one sulet
is there let me tell you about this one
so what happen is first of all what is
sulet
okay sulet is nothing but a Java class
which accept the incoming request
process it and Returns the response okay
so in you can say that it is a play like
a plain Java code itself it's our
business logic
sulet its purpose is that whatever the
uh request coming
in process it and return the response
also okay that's what sulet is you
remember that uh if you have worked in
monolithic Services right let's say that
we have rest apis
also we have soap API
also we have something called expose API
for file uploading multi multiple
different tasks so what we can do is we
can write different suets for this so I
can create one sulet which handles only
rest apis I can create another subet
which handles soap apis I can create
another sulet which can handle only file
uploads so multiple or you can say that
you can create one one more suets which
handle only static data like images or
something okay so when the request comes
to The sulet Container it decide that
hey this request will be handled by
which which sulet so each sulet can
configure that hey this rest API let's
say that this can configure the hey I
can handle
slash
API SL star so anything which is start
with/ API I can handle it okay similarly
soap API can provide some configuration
which sulet container will use and
decide which sulet to invoke now in the
microservices right and now let's say
that when we are discussing about spring
boot is specific and it's a microservice
let's say that it's not a monolithic
where I have static data also and
something soap apis and all so now when
you say that when we discuss more about
uh microservices and specifically spring
boot so there the need of multiple subet
are reduced in 2017 16 when we used to
code we used to have multiple subet and
this is suets are nothing but a plain
Java code right so whatever the
controller you are writing it just like
a specific apis like this is let's say/
API SL user another control / API SL
let's say order but here this sulet
accept anything SL API star so anything
start with/ API this dispatcher subet
will take care of it earlier we don't
used to have this controller in this
subet itself we used to have all the
code logic and we have Factory here okay
if it is user go and perform this logic
if it is order go and perform this logic
okay so what I mean to say here is that
now when we are specifically doing
microservices and spring boot the need
of multiple servlets has been reduced so
mostly our dispatcher subet if you see
the default configuration is uh slash
estess slash asress means anything any
API dispatcher subet would be able to
handle so whatever the request coming is
to the tomat if tomat seees that okay
request is started with Slash and
anything it will just pass it to the
dispatcher subet dispatcher subet will
pass it to one of the
controller okay so now you know what is
sulet okay and this is one I show that
we can create multiple sulet if we want
subet one I can configur it to rest API
subet 2 can be configured for soap apis
similarly dispatcher subet default is
slash this okay and today if even if you
want hey dispatcher ofet I only want to
hand SL
API SL asress that also you can do okay
I won't go further into that how you can
do it but in the at theate configuration
class itself you can do that you can
update this configuration to this and
only only those apis will comes to a
dispatcher sub not
all so with this diagram at least now we
are clear that filter is before the
request get assigned to a particular sub
and Interceptor is after one of the
subet is assigned specifically so this
is very very uh spring related part so
if I just uh pick a red color I would
say that this is very very specific to
Spring
framework so Interceptor is you can say
that two two points one
is after the sulet is
chosen and which sulet is specifically
spring boot so dispatcher sub is very
very specific for spring boot so
Interceptor is nothing but a spring boot
concept which I would say so once the
spring boot sulet which is dispatcher
sulet is
chosen so then before this dispatcher
subet assign the request to the
controller intercept
intercepted and for filter you can uh
say that before the sulet container
assign the request to one of the sulet
before for that itself filters comes
into the
picture so now you are clear that when
to use filter whenever you want to put a
logic which is common for all the suets
like spring boot
security like spring
boot
security so uh spring boot security is
uh uses filter because it it is applied
all HTTP request and response and
irrespective of of the suets because
it's a very very generic code it's not
very specific to our application or
something so it can be applied to
multiple suets also so that's why it
uses a filter so it it lies in this
area okay and whenever you want
something specific to your application
particular sulet okay I want let's say
this dispatcher subet so let's say that
call this as a rest API subet if
anything is specifics to rest API subet
then you can add Interceptor for this
okay so you got it anything is specific
to a particular sulet you can use
Interceptor anything which is common for
all the suets you can use
filter okay so this is what I have
explained it here so filter is used when
we want to intercept HTTP request and
response and logic agnostic of the
underlying cetes we can have many
filters and have ordering between them
you can provide an ordering which one to
run in which
orders similarly in intercept is used
when we want to intercept HTTP request
and response same and add logic specific
to a particular subet in this case uh
Interceptor is mostly a spring boot
concept you can say that so we can say
that uh specific to a spring boot subet
dispatcher subet so it intercept it
whatever the request request is coming
sulet container whatever the request is
coming to dispatch a sulet let's say out
of many let's assume that there are many
subet so whatever it is coming to
dispatch a subet this Interceptor will
only take your intercept that only it
can't intercept salet to a request right
so that's what I mean here it's specific
to a particular subid we can have many
interceptors and have ordering between
them two also this is also possible we
can have more than one interceptors also
I will tell you how you can have so here
multiple interceptors and its ordering
how to write
it so in previous video right I already
told you how you can add one Interceptor
I showed you by creating one custom
inter uh Interceptor and there we
discussed about preh handle post handle
after
completion okay so here I will show you
how you can add more than one
Interceptor and ordering
also so here if you see that one more
thing is the preh handle so preh handle
is something which returns true or false
right this post handle returns wide
after completion returns white this preh
handle returns true and false so if preh
handle return false next filter and
controller will not get invoked so here
in the code itself we can check uh so
here if you see uh what was that
dispatcher subet apply preh handle if
preh handle return Falls this become
come true and it will just simply
return okay your next your next
controller and next uh not next filter
next controller and next
Interceptor will not get invoked itself
so how to create how to add more than
one Interceptor so now let's say that
from the previous video you already know
that how to create one Interceptor
similarly I have created another
Interceptor and I have Auto wired here
and from previous video you also know
that how to register it similarly you
can also add one more time registry. add
Interceptor you can add the second one
also and you'll see that this sequence
is actually followed so since you added
my custom Interceptor one my custom
Interceptor 2 so this Interceptor would
be executed first this would be executed
second so now you have
Interceptor one
Interceptor 2 so when the request comes
in so request goes like this and
response goes like this so this is your
request and this is your response so
when the request comes in what it goes
one Interceptor one
request and then Interceptor 2 and when
the response goes out so response what
you will see Interceptor two will get
invoked first then Interceptor one
because Interceptor 2 Interceptor one
like this okay so here I'm showing you
the output right so only I have put a
cog in preh handle post handle and after
completion so here if you see when the
request comes in so this is the order is
maintained so Interceptor one it is
going first so first it will go inside
preh handle preh handle of Interceptor
one so request is coming right so
Interceptor one then Interceptor 2 so
inter Interceptor one then preh handle
of Interceptor
2 right then your code logic then your
code logic now it has to response goes
out right then post handle of
Interceptor 2
first post handle of Interceptor
one similarly after completion of two
and then one and ultimately it goes
out okay so this is how the sequence is
maintained
and how to add filter you can add your
filters also like here if you see either
Jakarta do suet you can use or here in
the Java X do you will find
filter you can choose any of this
Library so I'm creating my filter one
implement this filter so it has three
method in it do filter and Destroy so in
it like uh once the object of this my my
filter is get created this method is get
invoked only one time if you have to
initialize something generally I've
never seen we uh I have specifically
initialized something but even if let's
say you want to set up uh some name or
something you want to specifically
initialize something in this you can do
that right but this is the main part do
filter so do filter is like do
something before you process the request
so this is like do filter right
next here if there are multiple filter
filter 1 Filter 2 filter 3 So currently
let's say this my filter one after that
when you do do filter it will just call
the next thing if the next part is
Filter 2 it will call it if the next
part is let's say code logic itself no
more filter then code logic will get
invoked right and the similar behavior
is maintained in the filter also so when
the request comes in it goes in here
filter 1 Filter 2 filter 3 and the when
the response goes out it goes into
reverse filter 3 Filter 2 filter 1 so do
filter is nothing but process the rest
of the code if you are at filter one the
process next of the code is Filter 2 if
you are filter two next code is filter 3
if filter 3 next is your actual code
logic and then reverse so this is the
after processing
it similarly I have added another filter
my filter to imp imps filter the same
thing I've just puted the logic my
filter 2
inside process it something my filter 2
complete here my filter one is
there okay now this is the
configuration so here I am creating a
bean of my filter my first filter in
this I am doing its registration so this
is the process how you can create an
object of registration be you can set
the filter so I am creating a new object
because here if you see that I am not
putting at theate component otherwise I
don't have to create a new
object so I am creating an object what
is the
filter this filter can take care of what
all URL so I have put SL Asis right and
I have set the specific order to so just
specifically purposely I have given it
order two for the filter one and for
Filter 2 I have specifically given the
order one just to show you that uh
through this order we can maintain the
sequence similarly I created a second
filter so I have created an object of a
registration Bean set the filter for
this okay my filter two what all added
what all for this specific URL pattern
this filter will get invoke and the
order I have kept it one and I have
return this registration
Bean that's all now when you see the
output so now you have
Filter 2 and then filter 1 because its
order is
one for the filter 2 right and this
two I have specifically purposely
mentioned this so now when the request
comes in first it will invoke Filter
2 and then filter one and during the
response
reverse my filter 2 inside so first it
goes here my inside this one then it
will go what it would happen is it will
go inside this my filter two inside and
do do filter process rest of the code
now the process rest of the codee there
is more filter yes filter one so it will
goes to the next filter my filter in
filter one inside now this filter one it
goes inside printed this do filter means
process next of the code next of the
code no more filter so code logic will
run hitting so this is my business logic
code
logic now the response goes out so first
it will goes out of this my filter 1
completed and then after that it will
goes out of my filter 2
completed okay so this is how you can
create filter and if you add both
interceptors so if you add both the
logic from the above one right and you
run the output here if you see this
would happen so your is like sulet
container then filter then
sulet and then
controller so here you have uh this is
your filter and and this will be your
Interceptor so first filter will run my
filter one so I have just here by doing
that I just change the order properly
filter one I have changed the order to
one and filter two I change the order to
two just so that it meant it don't
confused like filter 1 Y is second so
I've corrected the order
here so now when the request so filter 1
Filter 2 then here we have
Interceptor one Interceptor 2 so now
request coming is inside filter
one then it goes inside uh Filter
2 right after filter to uh there is no
more filters so it will pass it to one
of the sub
and after the suet so this is your code
logic
here so after so this is your sulet now
suet before it pass to the controller it
will goes to the Interceptor one right
so inside preh handle of Interceptor one
now request goes to Interceptor 2 now
ultimately your code logic your
controller now the response goes out
right so first Interceptor two will get
invol right so this is all your
Interceptor so post handle of
Interceptor 2 post handle of Interceptor
1 then after completion of Interceptor 2
after completion of Interceptor one
ultimately filter
two and ultimately filter one and goes
out so you got it like how the sequence
generally maintain what's the difference
between uh filter and interceptor and
when to use it
see if somebody say that hey you can
change the header you can change the
request you can change the response you
can change it into Interceptor also you
can change it into filter
also but when to use right Interceptor
also has access to request and response
filter also has access to request and
response but the only thing is what
specific purpose you are using if it
says
generic no matter about suets different
different suets use it at filter if it
is very specific to you can say that a
spring framework and very very specific
to your one particular uh sulet then go
for
Interceptor okay I hope this clarifies
but if there is any out we can discuss
further and uh we'll see what question
can come in we can I'll try to answer
those and if you have any more
additional information information about
this that hey uh in this scenario filter
is better than Interceptor or this I
don't consider filter or Interceptor is
better or not both are totally different
both are totally different at different
places but still if you have uh such
points we can further discuss more on
that okay guys thank you bye